A Guide to the Robert N. Giaimo Papers 1980.0003
Archives and Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Library
Robert N. Giaimo Papers
undated, 1956-1981
Archives and Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Library
1980.0003
280 Linear Feet
Robert Nicholas was raised in North Haven, CT. Giaimo was a member of the 86th-96th Congresses from the Third District of Connecticut (New Haven area) from 1958-1980. During his twenty-two years, he served on the House Budget Committee, the House Commission on Information and Facilities, the Joint Committee on Intelligence, the House Appropriations Committee, and its subcommittees on Department of Defense, District of Columbia, Treasury Postal Service and General Government, Legislative Branch, and Housing and Urban Development.
Biography
Son of Rosario and Rose Scarpulla Giaimo, Robert Nicholas Giaimo was raised in North Haven, CT. He earned his A.B. from Fordham University (1941) and his LL.B. from the University of Connecticut School of Law in 1943. Giaimo married Marion Shuenemann of Windsor, CT, in 1945.
Giaimo was a member of the 86th-96th Congresses from the Third District of Connecticut (New Haven area) from 1958-1980. During his twenty-two years, he served on the House Budget Committee, the House Commission on Information and Facilities, the Joint Committee on Intelligence, the House Appropriations Committee, and its subcommittees on Department of Defense, District of Columbia, Treasury Postal Service and General Government, Legislative Branch, and Housing and Urban Development.
Robert N. Giaimo made many contributions during his 22 years in Congress. Among the most noteworthy are: co-sponsoring a bill that led to the creation of the National Endowment of the Arts and Humanities; leading the first successful effort to end funds for the fighting in Indochina; sponsoring a provision for eliminating the loyalty oath in the National Defense Education Act; and working for the inclusion of the old New Haven Railroad in the Penn Central merger.
Scope and Content
The collection documents the activities and interests of Robert Nicholas Giaimo, Third District Congressman for the 86th - 96th Congresses. The papers contain correspondence to and from constituents on legislation, subject files on proposed legislation, press releases and statements, scrapbooks, photographs, and sound recordings. The materials are a useful resource for examining the legislative process, as well as those issues of national and regional significance to the people of Connecticut. Subjects included in Series III, Legislative Correspondence include: General Powers, Consumer Affairs, Product Safety, Defense and National Security, Domestic Economy, Education, Environment, General Government, Health and Safety, House of Representatives, Housing and City Problems, International Relations, Judiciary Procedures, Labor-Management, Lobbyists and Pressure Groups, Poverty Programs, Social Security, Tariff and Trade, Taxation, Transportation, Veterans and Welfare. The House of Representatives section has been further divided into two subsections: First Session and Second Session. Subjects receiving the most attention include energy resources, gas crisis, abortion ("population control"), inflation, Watergate, impeachment proceedings against Richard Nixon and Nixon's pardon. Also of interest is some of the correspondence in the Civil Rights/General file concerning the seventy day occupation of Wounded Knee, South Dakota by members of the American Indian Movement (AIM).
Of interest within the Committee files are those relating to his position on funding for the Vietnam War and the extension of the war into Cambodia (found in 93rd Congress files, 1973-1974). Congressional Operations Committee files contain a notebook entitled "The Legislative Role of Congress in Gathering and Disclosing Information." Also of note, the Select Committee on Intelligence files contain data concerning the CIA and include newspaper clippings on the CIA, FBI>, political assassinations, intelligence recommendations and proposals.
Information on Giaimo's public position on issues and events can be found in Series VI, Press releases and Statements.
Arrangement
Series I: Voting Records (1958-1981) contains the official voting Record and ratings by special interest groups. Arranged chronologically by congressional session and alphabetically therein.
Series II: Legislation (1958-1981) contains copies of bills submitted or co-sponsored by Giaimo. Also includes agency reports, brochures, studies and other materials relevant to the proposed legislation, and constituent correspondence. A list of bills submitted accompanies the 86th - 87th and 89th - 92nd Congresses. There is a listing by topic of all bills submitted for all Congresses. The bills are divided into four types and are arranged by bill number within each type for each congressional session. The four types are: House Resolutions (HR), House Concurrent Resolutions (H.Con.Res.), House Resolutions (H.Res.), and House Joint Resolutions (H.J.Res.). The first box of this series (Box 4) contains bill summary sheets and a notebook of Giaimo proposed legislation.
Series III: Legislative Correspondence (1973-1981) consists of constituent correspondence regarding legislation and replies. Also included are clippings and publications. The files are arranged alphabetically within each session. General headings include: General Powers, Consumer Affairs, Product Safety, Defense and National Security, Domestic Economy, Education, Environment, General Government, Health and Safety, House of Representatives, Housing and City Problems, International Relations, Judiciary Procedures, Labor-Management, Lobbyists and Pressure Groups, Poverty Programs, Social Security, Tariff and Trade, Taxation, Transportation, Veterans and Welfare. The House of Representatives section has been further divided into two subsections: First Session and Second Session. Subjects receiving the most attention include energy resources, gas crisis, abortion ("population control"), inflation, Watergate, impeachment proceedings against Richard Nixon and Nixon's pardon. Also of interest is some of the correspondence in the Civil Rights/ General file concerning the seventy day occupation of Wounded Knee, South Dakota by members of the American Indian Movement (AIM).
Series IV: Committee Files (1961-1981) has five subseries: House Budget Committee, Appropriations Committee, Defense Appropriations Subcommittee, House Committee on Information and Facilities, Joint Committee on Coinage, Congressional Operations Committee, and Select Committee on Intelligence.
Series V: Outgoing Correspondence (1959-1980) contains copies of Giaimo's letters to constituents, federal agencies and branches, congressional committees, and other civic and political organizations. Arranged chronologically and alphabetically therein.
Series VI: Press Releases and Statements (1959-1980) includes releases and statements issued by Giaimo's office arranged chronologically.
Series VII: Project Files (1962-1980). The series includes materials in various municipalities, business agencies, and services which sought federal funding, in addition to constituent correspondence, clippings, subject files and publications. Includes four subseries: Connecticut Federal Grants and Contract Awards, Third District Towns, Case Files and Religious Cults.
Series VIII: Personal Papers (1961-1980) documents Giaimo's non-Congressional interests and activities. Subseries: United Democrats of Congress, (Henry) Jackson for President, Thank Yous and Praise, Tributes.
Series IX: Audio Visual Records (1956-1980)is divided into five subseries: Photographs, Reel to Reel Tapes, 16mm films, Cassettes and Videotapes. These materials support and supplement other series within the collection.
Series X: Plaques (1961-1978) given in recognition of Giaimo's work and support for the activities of specific agencies or organizations.
Series XI: Office Guest Books and Appointment Books (1959-1980). The appointment books are flagged for microfilming. The flags should not be removed.
Series XII: Scrapbooks (1956-1978). 21 books contain clippings, 4 contain photographs.
Acquisition Information
The papers were given to the University of Connecticut in December 1980 by Robert N. Giaimo.
Access
The collection is open and available for research.
Intelligence service; Loyalty oaths; Arts; Committees; Scrapbooks; Humanities; Budget; Budget--Law and legislation; New Haven (inhabited place); Video recordings; North Haven (inhabited place); Political participation; Vietnam War (1961-1975); Legislation; Legislative bodies; Indochina (general region); United States (nation); Connecticut (state); Correspondence; Publications (documents); Photographs; Endowments; Administrative records; Expenditures, Public; Financial Records; Politicians; Audio visual materials; United States. Congress. House. Select Committee on Intelligence.; United States. Congress. House; United States. National Defense Education Act of 1958.; United States. Congress. House. Committee on Appropriations.; United States. Congress. Joint Committee on Congressional Operations.; National Endowment for the Humanities; National Endowment for the Arts
- Series I: Voting Records, 1958-1981
  - 86th Congress, 1959-1960 (Box 1:, Folder 1)
  - 87th Congress, 1961-1962 (Box 1:, Folder 2)
  - 88th Congress, 1962-1964 (Box 1:, Folder 3)
  - 89th Congress, 1965-1966 (Box 1:, Folder 4)
  - 90th Congress, 1967-1968 (Box 1:, Folder 5)
  - 91st Congress, 1969-1970 (Box 1:, Folder 6)
  - 92nd Congress, 1971-1972 (Box 2:, Folder 7)
  - 93rd Congress, 1973-1974 (Box 2:, Folder 8)
  - 94th Congress, 1975-1976 (Box 2:, Folder 9)
  - 95th Congress, 1977-1978 (Box 2:, Folder 10)
  - 96th Congress, 1979-1980 (Box 2:, Folder 11)
  - Democratic National Committee Reports
    - 1958-1961 (Box 2:, Folder 12)
    - 1961-1965 (Box 2:, Folder 13)
    - 1965-1970 (Box 2:, Folder 14)
  - Democratic Congressional Campaign Reports
    - 95th Congress, 1st and 2nd Sessions (Box 2:, Folder 15)
  - Voting Record
    - 86th Congress (Box 2:, Folder 16)
    - 87th Congress (Box 2:, Folder 17)
    - 88th Congress (Box 2:, Folder 18)
    - 89th Congress (Box 2:, Folder 19)
    - 92nd Congress (Box 2:, Folder 20)
  - 92nd Congress Voting Record Ratings
    - American Security Council (Box 2:, Folder 21)
    - Americans for Democratic Action (Box 2:, Folder 22)
    - Common Cause (Box 2:, Folder 23)
    - League of Conservation Voters (Box 2:, Folder 24)
    - League of Women Voters (Box 2:, Folder 25)
    - COPE (Box 2:, Folder 26)
    - Labor (Box 2:, Folder 27)
  - 93rd Congress Voting Record Ratings (Box 3)
    - Americans for Constitutional Action (Box 3:, Folder 28)
    - The American Party (Box 3:, Folder 29)
    - A.F.S.C.M.E. (Box 3:, Folder 30)
    - American Anti-Vivisection Society (Box 3:, Folder 31)
    - ADA (Box 3:, Folder 32)
    - American Federation of Government Employees (Box 3:, Folder 33)
    - American Federation of Teachers (Box 3:, Folder 34)
    - Clothing Workers of America (Box 3:, Folder 35)
    - Common Cause (Box 3:, Folder 36)
    - Communication Workers of America (Box 3:, Folder 37)
    - Construction Workers (Box 3:, Folder 38)
    - Consumer Federation of America (Box 3:, Folder 39)
    - COPE (Box 3:, Folder 40)
    - Firemen and Oilers (Box 3:, Folder 41)
    - League of Conservation Voters (Box 3:, Folder 42)
    - League of Women Voters
      - North Haven (Box 3:, Folder 43)
      - Connecticut (Box 3:, Folder 44)
    - Government Standard (Box 3:, Folder 45)
    - Locomotive Engineers (Box 3:, Folder 46)
    - Nation's Business (Box 3:, Folder 47)
    - National Council of Senior Citizens (Box 3:, Folder 48)
    - National Education Association (Box 3:, Folder 49)
    - National Farmers Union (Box 3:, Folder 50)
    - National Federation of Independent Business (Box 3:, Folder 51)
    - National Organization of Women (Box 3:, Folder 52)
    - New Republic (Box 3:, Folder 53)
    - Operation Engineers (International) (Box 3:, Folder 54)
    - Patriotic Letter Writers (Box 3:, Folder 55)
    - Connecticut Audubon Council (Box 3:, Folder 56)
    - National Treasury Employees (Box 3:, Folder 57)
    - World Federalists USA (Box 3:, Folder 58)
    - Politics (Box 3:, Folder 59)
    - Ralph Nader Congress Report (Box 3:, Folder 60)
    - Tax Reform Research Group (Box 3:, Folder 61)
    - Teamsters (Box 3:, Folder 62)
    - United Auto Workers (Box 3:, Folder 63)
    - Amalgamated Clothing Workers (Box 3:, Folder 64)
  - 94th Congress Voting Record Ratings
    - Washington Office on Africa (Box 3:, Folder 65)
    - Liberty Lobby (Box 3:, Folder 66)
    - Consumer Federation of America (Box 3:, Folder 67)
    - DSG
      - Voting Survey (Box 3:, Folder 68)
    - Senior Citizens National Council (Box 3:, Folder 69)
    - United Auto Workers (Box 3:, Folder 70)
    - American Parent Committee (Box 3:, Folder 71)
    - Taxation with Representation (Box 3:, Folder 72)
    - Retail Clerks International Association (Box 3:, Folder 73)
    - Public Citizen (Box 3:, Folder 74)
    - Network (Catholic Organization) (Box 3:, Folder 75)
    - National Business (Box 3:, Folder 75)
    - Locomotive Engineers (Box 3:, Folder 76)
    - Government Standard (Box 3:, Folder 77)
    - League of Women Voters
      - Connecticut (Box 3:, Folder 78)
      - New Haven (Box 3:, Folder 79)
    - Independent Petroleum Association of America (Box 3:, Folder 80)
    - Fireman and Oilers (Box 3:, Folder 81)
    - Federation of American Business (Box 3:, Folder 82)
    - COPE, AFL-CIO (Box 3:, Folder 83)
    - Construction workers (Box 3:, Folder 84)
    - Connecticut Audubon Council (Box 3:, Folder 85)
    - Communication Workers of America (Box 3:, Folder 86)
    - Common Cause (Box 3:, Folder 87)
    - Clothing Workers of America (Box 3:, Folder 88)
    - Chamber of Commerce (Box 3:, Folder 89)
    - Building and Construction Trades (Box 3:, Folder 90)
    - American Federation of Teachers (Box 3:, Folder 91)
    - American Federation of Government Employees (Box 3:, Folder 92)
    - American Security Council (Box 3:, Folder 93)
    - American Conservation Union (Box 3:, Folder 94)
    - American Association of University Women (Box 3:, Folder 95)
    - American Vivisection Society (Box 3:, Folder 96)
    - A.F.S.C.M.E. (Box 3:, Folder 97)
    - The American Party (Box 3:, Folder 98)
    - Americans for Constitutional Action (Box 3:, Folder 99)
    - American Cause (Box 3:, Folder 100)
    - National Federation of Industrial Business (Box 3:, Folder 101)
    - Washington Monitor (Box 3:, Folder 102)
    - Coalition for New Foreign Policy (Box 3:, Folder 103)
    - Public Citizen (Box 3:, Folder 104)
    - The Machinists (Box 3:, Folder 105)
    - National Farmers Union (Box 3:, Folder 106)
    - Building and Construction Trades (Box 3:, Folder 107)
    - Right to Life (Box 3:, Folder 108)
    - Committee on National Legislation (Box 3:, Folder 109)
    - Committee for U.N. Reform (Box 3:, Folder 110)
    - National Small Business Association (Box 3:, Folder 111)
    - Committee for the Survival of Free Congress (Box 3:, Folder 112-113)
    - Retail Clerks International (Box 3:, Folder 114)
    - Bread for the World (Box 3:, Folder 115)
    - American Cause (Box 3:, Folder 116)
    - Record of Committee Chairman Candidates (Box 3:, Folder 117)
    - Council on National Priorities (Box 3:, Folder 118)
    - League of Conservative Voters (Box 3:, Folder 119)
    - National Federation of Independent Business (Box 3:, Folder 120)
    - United Mine Workers (Box 3:, Folder 121)
  - 95th Congress Voting Record Rating
    - General (Box 3:, Folder 122)
    - A.C.L.U. (Box 3:, Folder 123)
    - AFL-CIO (Box 3:, Folder 124)
    - ADA (Box 3:, Folder 125)
    - Food and Beverage Trade Department (Box 3:, Folder 126)
    - American Cause (Box 3:, Folder 127)
    - American Conservative Union (Box 3:, Folder 128)
    - American Council for World Freedom (Box 3:, Folder 129)
    - A.F.S.C.M.E. (Box 3:, Folder 130)
    - The American Patriot (Box 3:, Folder 131)
    - American Security Council (Box 3:, Folder 132)
    - American Society of Travel Agents (Box 3:, Folder 133)
    - Associated General Contractors (Box 3:, Folder 134)
    - Bread for the World (Box 3:, Folder 135)
    - ASARCO (Box 3:, Folder 136)
    - Brotherhood of Railway and Airline Clerks (Box 3:, Folder 137)
    - Chamber of Commerce (Box 3:, Folder 138)
      - Congressional Action (Box 3:, Folder 139)
    - Coalition for a New Foreign and Military Policy (Box 3:, Folder 140)
    - Common Cause (Box 3:, Folder 141)
    - Committee for the Survival of a Free Congress (Box 3:, Folder 142)
    - Congressional Quarterly Survey (Box 3:, Folder 143)
    - Consumer Federation of America (Box 3:, Folder 144)
    - Congress Watch (Nader) (Box 3:, Folder 145)
    - Conservative Caucus (Box 3:, Folder 146)
    - Fireman and Oilers Journal (Box 3:, Folder 147)
    - Friends Committee on National Legislation (Box 3:, Folder 148)
    - Ironworkers Political Action League (Box 3:, Folder 149)
    - League for Conservative Voters (Box 3:, Folder 150)
    - League of Women Voters (Box 3:, Folder 151)
    - Liberty Lobby (Box 3:, Folder 152)
    - I.A.M. (Box 3:, Folder 153)
    - National Alliance of Senior Citizens (Box 3:, Folder 154)
    - National Association of Businessmen (Box 3:, Folder 155)
    - National Association of Manufacturers (Box 3:, Folder 156)
    - National Abortion Rights Action League (Box 3:, Folder 157)
    - National Association for Uniformed Service (Box 3:, Folder 158)
    - National Education Association (Box 3:, Folder 159)
    - National Farmers Union (Box 3:, Folder 160)
    - National Federation of Independent Business (Box 3:, Folder 161)
    - T.R.I.M. (Box 3:, Folder 162)
    - National Opinion Poll (Box 3:, Folder 163)
    - Network (Box 3:, Folder 164)
    - PACE (Box 3:, Folder 165)
    - Politics Today (Box 3:, Folder 166)
    - Public Employees Department (Box 3:, Folder 167)
    - American Federation of Government Employees (Box 3:, Folder 168)
    - Retail Clerks International (Box 3:, Folder 169)
    - Sierra Club (Box 3:, Folder 170)
    - Taxation with Representation (Box 3:, Folder 171)
    - Teamsters (Box 3:, Folder 172)
    - Washington Office for Africa (Box 3:, Folder 173)
    - Democratic Congressional Committee Compilation (Box 3:, Folder 174)
    - DSG Special Report (Box 3:, Folder 175)
    - Reply to Law Attendance (Box 3:, Folder 176)
  - 96th Congress Voting Record Rating
    - General (Box 3:, Folder 177)
    - American Cause (Box 3:, Folder 178)
    - American Civil Liberties Union (Box 3:, Folder 179)
    - American Conservative Union (Box 3:, Folder 180)
    - Americans for Democratic Action (Box 3:, Folder 181)
    - AFL-CIO (Box 3:, Folder 182)
    - AFSCME (Box 3:, Folder 183)
    - American Parents Committee (Box 3:, Folder 184)
    - American Security Council (Box 3:, Folder 185)
    - Building and Construction Trades (Box 3:, Folder 186)
    - Coalition for New Foreign and Military Policy (Box 3:, Folder 187)
    - Common Cause (Box 3:, Folder 188)
    - Communications Workers of America (Box 3:, Folder 189)
    - Congress Watch (Nader) (Box 3:, Folder 190)
    - Conservative Caucus (Box 3:, Folder 191)
    - Consumer Federation of America (Box 3:, Folder 192)
    - Council for Competitive Economy (Box 3:, Folder 193)
    - Friends Committee on National Legislation (Box 3:, Folder 194)
    - I.A.M. (Box 3:, Folder 195)
    - League of Conservative Voters (Box 3:, Folder 196)
    - League of Women Voters (Box 3:, Folder 197)
    - Liberty Lobby (Box 3:, Folder 198)
    - National Association of Realtors (Box 3:, Folder 199)
    - National Council of Senior Citizens (Box 3:, Folder 200)
    - National Farmers Union (Box 3:, Folder 201)
    - National Federation of Independent Business (Box 3:, Folder 202)
    - National League of Cities (Box 3:, Folder 203)
    - National Opinion Poll (Box 3:, Folder 204)
    - National Small Business Association (Box 3:, Folder 205)
    - National Taxpayers Union (Box 3:, Folder 206)
    - Network (Box 3:, Folder 207)
    - The New England Council (Box 3:, Folder 208)
    - T.R.I.M. (Box 3:, Folder 209)
    - Teamsters (Box 3:, Folder 210)
    - United Food and Commercial Workers (Box 3:, Folder 211)
- Series II: Legislation, 1958-1981
  - Guide to Legislation 86th - 90th Congresses (Box 4:, Folder 212)
  - Legislation enacted (Box 4:, Folder 213)
  - Bills and Summary Sheets, 86th - 96th (Box 4:, Folder 214)
  - Notebook, Giaimo Legislation (Box 4:, Folder 215)
  - 87th Congress, 1961-1962 (Box not specified)
    - HR 1868—Relief of Anna and Amato Guerra (Box 5:, Folder 216)
    - HR 2894—Shellfish Research Center (Box 5:, Folder 217-218)
    - HR 3381—Relief of Benedetto and Annunziata Mariani (Box 5:, Folder 219)
    - HR 3756—Rehabilitation Services (Box 5:, Folder 220)
    - HR 4104—Practical Nurses Training (Box 5:, Folder 221)
    - HR 4673—Public Use of Shoreline Areas (Box 5:, Folder 222)
    - HR 5201—Immigration Amendment, Quotas (Box 5:, Folder 223)
    - HR 5530—Distressed Areas (Box 5:, Folder 224-225)
    - HR 5666—Pre WWI Mexican Border Service, Pension (Box 5:, Folder 226)
    - HR 6530—Commemorative Stamp, Old Stone Church, E. Haven (Box 5:, Folder 227)
    - HR 6531—Amendment, Water Pollution Act (Box 5:, Folder 228-229)
    - HR 7216—Aid to Higher Education (Box 5:, Folder 230)
    - HR 8214—Construction Tools/Explosives on Capitol Grounds (Box 5:, Folder 231)
    - HR 8713—Prevention of Juvenile Delinquency (Box 5:, Folder 232)
    - HR 8897—Teachers of Handicapped Children (Box 5:, Folder 233)
    - HR 8900—Aid to Education (Box 5:, Folder 234)
    - HR 9524—Taxation of Rights to Copyrights (Box 5:, Folder 235)
    - HR 10122—Federal Advisory Council on the Arts (Box 5:, Folder 236-237)
    - HR 10123—Improvement of Special Education Services (Box 5:, Folder 238)
    - HR 10124—Civil Remedies for Unfair Commercial Practices (Box 5:, Folder 239)
    - HR 10125—Expansion of State Programs for Exceptional Children (Box 5:, Folder 240)
    - HR 10170—Taxation of Transfers of Copyrights (Box 5:, Folder 241)
    - HR 10398—Federal Assistance of Technical Education (Box 5:, Folder 242)
    - HR 11826—Amendment of Immigration and Nationality Act (Box 5:, Folder 243)
    - HR 11902—President's Advisory Council on Education (Box 5:, Folder 244)
    - HR 12003—Coordinated Mass Transportation System (Box 5:, Folder 245)
    - HR 12029—Library Funding (Box 5:, Folder 246)
    - HR 12070—Taxation of Copyright Transfers (Box 5:, Folder 247)
    - HR 12222—Federal Water Pollution Control Administration (Box 5:, Folder 248)
    - HR 12506—Tax Assessments, Interstate Commerce (Box 5:, Folder 249-250)
    - HR 12507—Contracts, Competitive bidding (Box 5:, Folder 251)
    - HR 15238—Special Education (Box 5:, Folder 252)
    - HJRes 732—Multi-State Authority, Rail System (Box 5:, Folder 253)
    - Weekly Publication: Legislation of the 87th Congress (Box 5:, Folder 254)
    - Giaimo Educational Amendments (Box 5:, Folder 255)
    - Bigotry (Box 5:, Folder 256)
    - Anti-Semitic (Box 5:, Folder 257)
    - Rural Electrification (Box 5:, Folder 258)
  - 88th Congress, 1963-1964 (Box not specified)
    - HR 325—Materials and Correspondence (Box 6:, Folder 259-262)
    - HR 326—Amendment to Library Services Act (Box 6:, Folder 263)
    - HR 448—Technical Education and Correspondence (Box 6:, Folder 264)
    - HR 993—Shoreline Preservation and Correspondence (Box 6:, Folder 265)
    - HR 1913—Comprehensive Mass Transit and Correspondence (Box 6:, Folder 266)
    - HR 3305—Cooperative Education Centers (Box 6:, Folder 267)